

# João Pedro Dias

#### ENGINEER, DEVELOPER, RESEARCHER, AMATEUR PHOTOGRAPHER,

Porto, Portugal

☑ jpmdias@fe.up.pt | ♠ jpdias.me | ☑ jpdias | ☒ joaopdias | Ў jpd1as | ☒ jpdias

## **Summary**

Current Researcher at INESC TEC and pursuing a PhD degree in Informatics Engineering. Graduated from the Integrated Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, I'm passionate about technology, with a special focus on security and privacy, web development, data mining & Internet of Things. Besides that, I'm also an amateur photographer, football player, book lover and science addict.

## Education\_

### **Doctoral Program in Informatics Engineering - ProDEI (PhD)**

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2016-Exp. 2020

• Title: Towards a Reference Architecture for Orchestrating Large-Scale Internet of Things' Systems using Visual Programming Languages

#### Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering – MIEIC (MSc)

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2011-2016

- GPA: 15 out of 20
- Volunteer at Semana Profissão: Engenheiro (SPE) 2014 & 2016

#### **Sciences and Technologies**

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

Externato de Vila Meã

2008-2011

GPA: 17 out of 20

## **Experience**

# INESC TEC – Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering, Technology and Science | CSIG – Centre for Information Systems and Computer Graphics

University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

May 2017 – Today

• Researching in the area of Internet of Things, with special focus on Blockchain and Healthcare applications, in the scope of the project NanoSTIMA: *Macro-to-Nano Human Sensing: Towards Integrated Multimodal Health Monitoring and Analytics*.

## LIACC - Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory

University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

Sept. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Researching data representation and data mining applications on railway transportation systems in the scope of the project PEDDIR: Weigth in Motion and Wheels Defect Detection.
- Technologies: MongoDB, Python and Web Development | Project details: www.peddir.eu & www.in2rail.eu

ShiftForward, S.A. Porto, Portugal

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- Development of a Deploy Logger Service, a service for documenting and recording the release of new product versions over time.
- Technologies: Scala and Backbone. js | Project details: shiftforward.github.io/malamute/

#### Centro Hospitalar do Tâmega e Sousa, E.P.E.

Penafiel, Porto, Portugal

IT DEPARTMENT INTERNSHIP

Jul. 2014 – Aug. 2014

- · Development of an expedient management system for replacing the existent system based on paper archives.
- Technologies: MySQL and PHP

## **Additional Training**

2017 **Project Management**, ERASMUS+ Mobility for teaching FEUP, Porto, Portugal

2016 AWS Technical Essentials Online, Amazon Web Services – Training and Certification Online

2015 **Practical Workshop in Agile Project Management,** Strongstep - Innovation in UPTEC, Porto, Portugal

Software Quality
2015 **CERN Spring Campus**, CERN - European Organization for Nuclear Research

Lisbon, Portugal

2014 M101JS: MongoDB for Node.js Developers, MongoDB University

Online

Skills.

**Programming** Python **=** • Node.JS **=** • C/C++ **=** • Scala **=** • Java **=** • C# **=** • PHP **=** 

Web Technologies HTML5 = • CSS = • JavaScript = • Laravel(PHP) = • Flask(Python) = • Bootstrap(CSS) = • ¡Query(JS) =

**Databases** MySQL **=** • PostgreSQL **=** • InfluxDB **=** • MongoDB **=** 

**Others** Arduino ≡ • Git ≡ • Android ≡ • Windows Apps ≡ • Docker ≡ • Computer Security ≡ • LaTeX ≡

**Languages** Portuguese (Mother-tongue) **=** • English **=** 

## Publications \_\_\_\_

## CONFERENCE ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

2017 **Patterns for Things that Fail**, António Ramadas, Gil Domingues, João Pedro Dias, Ademar Aguiar, Hugo Sereno Ferreira

24<sup>th</sup> Conference on Pattern Languages of Programs (PLoP 2017) { DOI: To Appear }

2017 Towards a Framework for Agent-based Simulation of User Behaviour in E-Commerce Context, Duarte Duarte, João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira and Zaf. Kokkinogenis 15<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Practical Applications of Agents and Multi-Agent Systems (PAAMS'17) { DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-61578-3 3 }

2017 Automating the Extraction of Static Content and Dynamic Behaviour from e-Commerce Websites, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira 8<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT'17) { DOI: 10.1016/j.procs.2017.05.355 }

2017 **A hands-on approach on botnets for behavior exploration**, João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz

2<sup>nd</sup> International Conference on Internet of Things, Big Data and Security (IoTBDS 2017)

{ DOI: 10.5220/0006392404630469 }

#### **OTHERS**

2017 **Automating the Extraction of Static Content and Dynamic Behaviour from e-Commerce Websites**, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

 $10^{th}\ \text{Meeting}$  of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2017)

2016 A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose, João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz
 9<sup>th</sup> Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2016)

**DISSERTATIONS** 

2016 Reverse Engineering Static Content and Dynamic Behaviour of E-Commerce Sites for Fun and Profit, Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira | Grade of 17 out of 20.
Master's Dissertation, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/85374 }

Porto, Portugal

Porto, Portugal

Porto, Portugal

Porto, Portugal

2

Vancouver, Canada

Porto, Portugal

Madeira, Portugal

Porto, Portugal

Porto, Portugal

Porto, Portugal

### **Educational & Scientific Activities**

#### MASTER'S DISSERTATION CO-SUPERVISING

2017 Serverless Architectural Design for IoT Systems by Duarte Pinto, Supervised by Hugo

 Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto

2017 Exploring BlockChain as an Authentication and Security Mechanism for IoT by

Guilherme Pinto, Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics

and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto

2016 Interoperability In Software Applications For Smart Cities: Towards A Reference

Architecture by José Pedro Pinto, Supervised by Rosaldo Rossetti, PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto

## PROGRAM COMMITTEES & REVIEWS

## João Pedro Dias · Curriculum Vitae

California, USA 2017 IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IEEE IV'17), Reviewer 2017 IEEE 20th International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (IEEE Yokohama, Japan ITSC 2017), Reviewer **Conference Organization** 2018 **Conference Organization Chair**, DSIE'18 – 13th Doctoral Symposium in Informatics Porto, Portugal 2018 **Advisor Board Member**, Talk a Bit – Technology Conference, 6th Edition (2018) Porto, Portugal 2017 **Student Volunteer (Media Coverage)**, EPIA 2017 – 18<sup>th</sup> EPIA Conference on Artificial Porto, Portugal 2017 Web Communication Co-chair, ACM CarSys 2017 – The Second ACM International Utah, USA Workshop on Smart, Autonomous, and Connected Vehicular Systems and Services, part of the The 23<sup>rd</sup> Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom 2017) 2017 **Advisor Board Member**, Talk a Bit – Technology Conference, 5th Edition (2017) Porto, Portugal 2016 Conference Chair, Talk a Bit – Technology Conference, 4th Edition (2016) Porto, Portugal 2016 Web Communication Co-chair, 2016 IEEE 19th International Conference on Intelligent Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Transportation Systems (ITSC 2016) 2014 **Student Volunteer**, Inter-University Programming Marathon (MIUP 2014) Porto, Portugal 2014 **Student Volunteer**, INForum - Symposion on Informatics (INForum 2014) Porto, Portugal Invited Talks & Workshops \_\_\_ Information Systems and Software Engineering Seminars (SESI & SES) Lisboa, Portugal HOSTED AT FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF PORTO FOR STUDENTS OF THE MIEIC & MESW DEGREES Sept. 2017 • **Seminar**: How to Kill Your Privacy and IoT Your Home Along the Way. Pixels Camp 2017 Lisboa, Portugal HOSTED BY BRIGHT PIXEL AND BETA-I Sept. 2017 • Workshop: PiHeadquarters or How to Take Control of your House with Raspberry Pi and Docker. OPOSEC Meetup: [0x33] - The Meet Porto, Portugal HOSTED BY BLIP.PT Apr. 2016 • **Presentation**: A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose. **ShARE World Seminar 2015 –** "Europe vs. Asia: Grass Is Always Greener On The Other Side" FEUP, Porto, Portugal HOSTED BY SHARE GLOBAL STUDENT THINK TANK March 2015 • Workshop: How To Create Your First Personal Webpage.

2017 PC Member, IEEE S3C 2017 - 2017 IEEE Summer School on Smart Cities

Pro Bono Activity \_\_\_\_\_

#### **ACADEMIC**

#### **IEEE University of Porto Student Branch**

Porto, Portugal

STUDENT MEMBER

2012 – Today

Natal, Brazil

**EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE (SECRETARY)** 

2013 - 2015

- As a voluntary member I had organized and co-organized some workshops (C#, Photography, ETpX, Web Development) and other events including IEEE Day, IEEEXtreme and IEEEmadC.
- · As secretary I was also responsable for mantain the minutes of all meetings and other paperwork.

#### HUMANITARIAN

#### Luz da Vida Youth Group

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

2009 - 2011 FOUNDER MEMBER

· Founder and former active member, I had taken part of large number of activities on behalf of the village community.

## Honors & Awards

## INTERNATIONAL

2017	<b>847</b> <sup>th</sup> (of 2815), Google Hash Code 2017, hashcode.withgoogle.com	Online – Porto, Portugal
2015	<b>189<sup>th</sup> (of 2477)</b> , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 9.0, <i>sites.ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2014	<b>Honorable Mention</b> , IEEEmadC – Mobile Application Dev. Contest, <i>ieeemadc.org</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	<b>126<sup>th</sup> (of 7500)</b> , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 7.0, <i>sites.ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	<b>2<sup>nd</sup> Place</b> , European BEST Engineering Competition, <i>ebec.best.eu.org</i>	Warsaw, Poland

## DOMESTIC

2011 1<sup>st</sup> Place, PmatE Mat12 – Mathematics Competition, *pmate.ua.pt* 2009 2<sup>nd</sup> Place, PmatE Fis12 – Physics Competition, *pmate.ua.pt*

University of Aveiro, Portugal University of Aveiro, Portugal